It's great to have you here, Jan, just
in time.
Or, well, a few minutes late, but
anyways.
So, today we'll talk about embodied AI.
I know that's a topic that's, you know,
you're passionate about. Also a topic
topic that I'm I'm also
quite excited about.
Actually, both of us, I think, for many
years.
But I think now a lot more people,
you know, this is really kind of coming
a lot of There's a lot of excitement, a
lot of investments, a lot of things
going on. And so I think we'll dig a
little bit deeper in what's already
possible,
what we see on the horizon, the gaps
that we see,
the kind of things that are needed,
etc., etc. So, um
So maybe first embodied AI, what are we
talking about? So it's really
um
you know, AI that can actually
perceive in the world, understand the
situation, be able to reason about that,
plan
based on that, and then act in the
world. So that's really what we're
talking about. This can
go from
self-driving vehicles to then also, you
know, humanoid robots and and things
like that, and anything in between, I
would say.
um
So, Jan,
you know, like maybe we can start
where are we today? Like what can we do?
What can't we do? Can
So we're not very far.
uh
You know, we have So first of all, it's
not just embodied AI in the in the sense
of you know, robots and things like
that. It's also disembodied physical AI.
AI for the real world, right? So there's
a lot of systems
in the world that need to be understood,
predicted, controlled, which are not
necessarily bodies, right? It could be
it could be a manufacturing process,
could be a turbojet engine, it could be
you know, any kind of um industrial
process.
um Anything that's physical, anything
for which the data
comes to you in a form of
a sequence of high-dimensional,
continuous, noisy um signals. Video is
the best example.
Proprioceptive sensors on a robot is
another good example.
But there is a lot of applications of
this that have nothing to do with with
robotics, right? So, um So it's anything
that is not language-related. That's
that's really the the better definition,
right?
So,
the real world is fundamentally
different from language. And the reason
language has been like LLMs have been so
successful is because language is easy.
um
You know, we have
systems that can pass the bar exam.
I'm not going to say they're as smart as
a lawyer. I don't know if there's any
lawyer in the room here. No, we're all
scientists and engineers here, so I can
say that.
um
And
so we have systems that can pass the bar
exam.
They can also, you know, do math, right?
Solve equations, they can write code.
Many of us here write code, too.
uh
But
they don't really deal with the real
world, right? Which is the reason why we
don't have domestic robots, we don't
have level five self-driving cars still.
um At least not at the consumer level.
And so we and, you know, human humanoid
robots
>> but not level five. No level five. And
uh
And even at level four, you know, we
cheat a lot.
I think level four less than way more. I
think you can claim that they achieve
level four. They do.
>> But not level five. They need full maps,
they need control of where they are and
when they operate.
>> And they need, you know, exotic sensors,
lidars, and complete
>> okay. That's okay. That's fine.
>> can cheat. It's It's perfectly I don't
think that's cheating, by the way. No,
no. I mean, it's okay.
But it's expensive in the sense that how
is it that a 17-year-old can learn to
drive in, you know, 10 to 20 hours of
practice?
uh And we have millions of hours of
training data that we could, in
principle, train a machine learning
system by imitation to imitate human
drivers. But that doesn't work. You
don't get reliable
driving systems this way. And so,
um
that sort of leads me to another
statement about
robotics. There's a lot of companies
building humanoid robots, and they do
those kinds of, you know, they play kung
fu and,
you know, impressive thing. This is all
precomputed.
Okay? uh
None of those company, absolutely none
of them, has any idea how to make those
robots smart enough to be useful.
Right? It's a big secret of
robotics industry.
um You can train them on very narrow
tasks.
And you have to to collect lots and lots
of data the same way, you know, people
thought they would build self-driving
cars.
um And it's expensive, and it's only
practical for a small number of narrow
tasks, and you you don't have robots
that, you know, have nearly as good as a
common sense as your house cat,
let alone human intelligence, right? So,
um that's the
you know, that's the challenge for the
next few years, right? Getting a system
to really understand the real world. And
the problem is that the approaches that
have been successful for language do not
work for high-dimensional, continuous,
noisy data. You have to use something
else.
So, um you know, so let's let's actually
start with
you know, with what people are trying
now in in robotics and in in in embodied
AI. So,
you know, and and I know your positions
on on LLMs and what what you can do with
them. uh I agree with you, language is
is easy because in a sense we
immediately start at a semantic level.
We have, you know, tokens are
essentially very close to like a
semantic concept. um And so directly by
working at that level, we can ignore a
lot of the noisy, complicated,
real-world kind of things. You know, we
say car, and we can imagine many many
different things, and so on. uh But, you
know, for an LLM, it's just kind of a
car with, you know, some dimensions with
it, but kind of some concepts associated
with it, but but but like no
understanding what it actually is,
right? um
just having correlations to other stuff.
Anyway, so there's LLMs, there's then
there's then VLMs,
and there's VLAs now that there's a lot
of excitement around, right? uh I Well,
you know, not by you, but but by others.
So, but but I'd like you to a little bit
kind of
explain like the relationship between
all of those those three, and and you
know, also where you see the
shortcomings there. Right. So VLM is,
you know, basically the idea of
mixing in
visual representations together with
language, with tokens that come from
language. um And then use the machinery
of LLMs basically to do to do that. uh
VLAs
are kind of a version of this where the
output of the system is a sequence of
actions.
There's a major flaw with those
approaches, and they're extremely
difficult extremely difficult to make
them work. The VLAs or or so-called
agentic systems only work in situations
where
the actions obey a
a script that you have to basically
repeat all the time.
um
You know, repetitive task of some kind.
So it's a new way of just designing
automating a task, which is data-driven
instead of being, you know,
programmatic. uh But it's very brittle,
it's very restricted to very narrow
applications for which there is a you
know, a script that you can follow.
That's not what you want. You want a
system that can accomplish a new task
it's never been trained to accomplish,
which every human is capable of doing,
every animal even, uh facing a new
situation using
their mental model of the world. Okay,
so here we're going to talk about world
models. A world model is a big buzzword
now, but mostly
but people mean different things for
this. And And it's mostly a buzzword in
research, not so much in industry. The
AI industry is completely LLM-pilled, as
they say.
uh
And and in Silicon Valley, everybody is
working on the same thing. They're all
digging the same trench. They're
stealing each other's engineers so that
they they can't afford to do something
different because if they start going on
a tangent, they're going to,
you know, fall behind the other guys.
And so they're all doing the same thing,
and that's one big reason I left Meta,
right? Because Meta also became
LLM-pilled.
um
You know, with sort of recent research
thing.
And it's fine, you know, it's a
strategic decision that
maybe makes sense for for them. Just not
what I'm interested in. uh And so, um
I cannot imagine that we can build
agentic systems without those systems
having an ability to predict in advance
what the consequences of their actions
are going to be.
The way
we act in the world is that we know what
the we can predict the consequence
consequences of our actions.
And that's what allows us to plan.
um So what is a world model? Given the
state of a environment, a system you
want to control at time T, and given an
action or intervention you imagine
taking,
can you predict the state of the world
or the of the or the system at time T
plus one? If you have, that's a world
model. You don't do this at the pixel
level if it's video.
uh You do this in an abstract
representation space. And that's a
crucial key
insight that you you you know, you need
to really understand. You cannot predict
every detail, for example, what is going
to happen in the video.
I can take a video of this room, rotate
the camera, and stop here, and then ask
the system continue the video. System
will predict, you know, where the room
is, probably, you know, a door at some
point. There's no way it can predict
what all of you looks like. There's
absolutely no way in hell I can predict
the texture of your beautiful
uh
dress here, which is, you know, very
shiny, and uh
which has, you know, a huge amount of
information. It's just impossible,
right? So if you train a generative
architecture, which is supposed to
predict at the pixel level, it fails. It
doesn't do anything useful for you. I
mean, it might produce cute videos or
cute pictures with diffusion models, but
that's it.
And it it will not understand the
underlying structure of of the world.
For that, you need to find an abstract
representation of of uh
of reality that allows you to make
predictions and eliminate all the
details you cannot predict. And we'll
come we'll come back to that. I first
want to take a step back to um you know,
to the the VLM and and VLA world uh and
and LM world. I think you said like you
can only do things that are essentially
scripted and this and that.
But I would say in industry, there are
many many things that are useful and
that are scripted and you know, you have
to carry out a certain task and most of
the time you have to do it. So
So, I would say there is probably a lot
of potential for the current this
current technology to actually deliver
value
uh with today's state. Like if you look
at you know, VLMs essentially, you know,
we it's it's it's text and I agree it's
actually really text first and then you
know, an image is worth a thousand uh
tokens literally pretty much. Um and so
uh and then you know, with with action
it's you still essentially take a
picture. This is the situation.
This is what I want to do and then you
know, like from that you kind of if it's
all scripted kind of in a sense, you can
kind of carry it out, right? And you can
build
you can program it. It's probably a
simpler way to program than maybe what
we used to do before. So So So, let's
say you know, like if if if you would be
an advocate of VLAs or so, like what do
you think we can all achieve already
with what we have today? Well, I mean,
it's like LLMs. Those things are useful.
And there is probably a number of uh
applications probably relatively
narrow narrower than what people are
thinking
for which those things would be useful
and practical and deployable. But you
know, I old enough to remember what
happened in the 1980s with the expert
systems. Okay, expert systems, you know,
you
you were going to
the coolest job at the time was going to
be uh knowledge engineer. You were you
were going to sit down next to a human
expert and then trans translate the
knowledge of the human expert in rules
and facts. Okay, in a and then use a
inference engine to basically replace
the expert or you know, kind of clone
the expert if you want. No machine
learning whatsoever. It was entirely
human.
That approach to AI essentially failed
because the the brittleness of the
resulting system and the cost of
of this, you know, knowledge transfer
into a machine was just too high. So,
there was a very narrow number of
applications for which it it was
practical. It's going to be the same
thing for VLA. It's going to be a
relatively small number of applications
where you have scripted, you know,
scenarios where those things are going
to be useful. Um but in the end, if you
are interested like I am in, you know,
building systems that have the
intelligence of let's say a cat, you
know, let alone humans. Um
you need common sense. You need the
ability to predict
uh the consequences of your actions. You
need the ability to plan. You need the
ability to reason. And you're not going
to get this with a with VLA or VLM or
LLMs or any generative architectures.
>> I agree, but I would say, you know, I
see a lot of potential industry of just
you know, doing what you're supposed to
do.
>> I mean, LLMs are super useful for
coding, you know, no question. Well,
okay. So So, back to um you know, to
world models. Um so you said like you
need to you know, maybe not predict at a
pixel level. Now, sometimes you can I
mean like video models actually do very
nice work in particular when you know,
say like like with a VLA when you're
given a starting position. You know,
this is the situation and I have to
predict now I'm I just need to do a
relatively simple task. I need to move a
few things around, kind of assemble
something or so.
There I can probably predict at a pixel
level exactly how it should look like,
right?
Um so So, I think sometimes, you know,
there are situations where you can
actually go to the pixel level.
Um I know of course, you know, like
you're a strong proponent of of all the
of the Jepa framework of of going to um
you know, I agree with you. You don't
have to predict every pixel for most
situations. I think sometimes you do
like when you really want a fine scale
thing in the end, you might need detail.
My question is actually where
you know, how do we find What is the
right level at which we and I think it's
not always the same necessarily for for
every task. So, what is the right level
of abstraction at which we need to
predict? I mean, we as humans
we do indeed always or you know, our
whole brain seems to be dedicated to
predicting the future.
And then we look at the differences,
right? And and and we might care about
them or not. Uh and indeed we we I think
we actually don't predict I mean, even
most of the Jepa maybe I'm wrong, but
it's predicting at a certain level of
abstraction. Uh mostly at a fixed level
that's learned of abstraction. Um
intuitively, I would actually like to be
able to predict throughout the levels
and go to the level I want. Yeah.
>> Yeah, totally. No, I mean, you
you know, picking the right level of
abstraction is absolutely essential to
understanding the world around us.
Um in fact, we don't know any other way
of doing it. It's it's something that,
you know, not many people realize, but
um
let's say
let's say I want to plan a trip from New
York to Paris. Let's say I'm sitting in
my office in New York. It's midday and I
want to be in Paris tomorrow.
Uh I cannot possibly plan my entire trip
to Paris in terms of elementary actions
for humans, which are millisecond by
millisecond muscle control.
Right? Cuz
it's too complicated. I have a planning
issue and I just don't have the
information.
You know, I don't know
if someone is going to run into me when
I walk to the elevator. I don't know if
how long I'm going to have to wait for a
taxi. Right? So, I cannot plan, but I
can plan at a very abstract level.
At the abstract level, I can say, well,
I need to go to the airport and catch a
plane. Okay, now I have a sub goal,
being at the airport.
My new objective is being close to the
airport, right? Um I'm in New York, so I
go down on the street and hail a taxi.
Okay, that's a two-action plan, but it's
very high level.
Very little information I need to know
uh other than maybe the condition of
traffic. It would determine whether I
take a taxi or subway or helicopter. Um
then
you know, then how do I go to on the
street? I go to the elevator, push the
button, walk out walk out of the
building. How do I go to the elevator?
You know, so at some point in the
hierarchy you get down to a point where
you can just take the action because you
know how to stand up from your chair and
walk to the door and open the door and
things like that, right? So, this this
is called hierarchical planning. It's
completely unsolved problem in AI.
People have
you know, mostly given up.
But that's basically what really is uh
a big challenge that we we should crack
uh for for kind of future AI systems
that can behave properly. Animals do
this all the time. Humans are much
better at abstractions than humans, but
but animals do this.
Um
so, that requires
a multi-level
world model. Right? A low-level world
model that predicts short-term with a
lot of details, with low-level actions.
Okay, if I send a particular command to
my muscle, it's going to move my arm in
a particular way, right? Or high-level
actions, you know, uh
um
hailing a taxi to go to the airport.
That's more of a high-level action.
Um the low level is not describable in
language.
Uh some part of the high level is and if
it's a normal script, maybe VLA will,
you know, do something like that. But um
but really what you need for all of this
is a mental model that allows you to
predict what the consequence of your
actions, regardless of the levels, are
going to be. So, how do you train a
hierarchical model of this type? So,
first of all, you have to realize that
you cannot make prediction
in pixel space, in input space. You have
to make prediction in that abstract
representation space.
And when you train that, so this is
called this is the Jepa architecture
that uh Mark was just mentioning, right?
So, Jepa means joint embedding
predictive architecture and it means
learning an abstract representation of
the input signal
and making prediction in that abstract
representation space and training this
whole thing at once.
Uh
and the prediction might be conditioned
by an action that you imagine taking,
which gives you a world model.
Um so
the abstraction level
that this system is going to learn
depends on the horizon that you train it
to make predictions at, right? If you
train the system to make prediction
you know, 10 milliseconds in the future,
it's going to make very accurate
predictions in the short term. Those
predictions are going to diverge from
reality really quickly. So, there you
have to go
one level up.
Maybe predict 1/10 of a second or a
second in the future. And then the
higher you go in the hierarchy, the
longer term
uh the predictions are. I could in
principle describe everything that is
taking place in this room here between
us
in terms of uh quantum field theory.
All right, that'd be crazy.
But it would be a
you know, a very accurate description of
everything that takes place here,
including the neurochemistry of our
brain processes and what we think and
everything, right? But it's completely
impractical. I would need to measure the
wave function
you know, of of this room and probably
like a cubic kilometer around us. Um
and then you're using use some
ridiculously powerful quantum computer
to actually do the simulation. Like we
don't do this, right?
Uh
so, we invent abstractions in science,
but also that's what we do when we
perceive and understand the world. We
invent abstractions like particles,
atoms, molecules. In the living world,
it's proteins, organelles, cells,
organisms,
societies, ecosystems.
And the the right level at which to
describe what's going on in this room
now is, you know, psychology, economics
and science, right? It's pretty high in
the hierarchy. We're not going to
predict like, you know, the reaction of
all of us in terms of particle physics.
Uh that's impossible. So, being able to
ignore details that are irrelevant that
you cannot predict so that you can make
long-term prediction is absolutely
crucial to intelligence and
generative models do not allow you to do
this. This is what Jepa enables.
But Jepa at this point still is
typically at a particular for particular
task, it learns a particular level of
abstraction that's Well, that's what you
see in publications, but
Okay.
We're working on multi-level Okay. Okay.
>> hierarchies. Okay. So,
in terms of
you know, to to act in the
uh
you know, in in in the physical world,
um
what are the sensing modalities that,
you know, that you think
uh we need? So, like now we narrow it
down a little bit to like, you know,
maybe more like really robot like
robotics applications, right? Um What do
you see as as kind of um useful um
kind of you know, where where both have
a background in vision or so so we of
course will use cameras or or you know,
vision sensors, but but what else is
needed uh to to make things work? So,
what what is a you know, what would be
the appropriate world model for for
robot? Um there's several component.
There's first
a a model a mechanical sort of
mechanical dynamical model of the robot,
which, you know, you apply a torque to a
a motor in one of the joints, right? And
the
the arm or the legs moving a particular
way.
You can actually write down such
dynamical models with a bunch of
equations. This is what classical
robotics uh is about, and you can use
this model to do motion planning to some
extent. It doesn't work that well
actually for complex actions. But all
those those videos of, you know, kung fu
playing robots, that's that's what they
do. It's all planned in advance using
handwritten models.
They're fine-tuned a little bit using
reinforcement learning and stuff, but
it's kind of a minor
minor step. Um
But then there is the model of the world
around the robot. Can you predict what,
you know, other people are going to do,
you know, whether this object is about
to fall, you know, going to catch it,
you know, things like that. So, it's a
model of intuitive physics. How do you
learn that? You learn that We learn that
as babies by watching the world go by.
And it takes 9 months for a human baby
to learn gravity, to learn that objects
that are not supported fall.
Um 6-month-old babies haven't yet
integrated the idea that objects, you
know, don't float in the air.
Uh
but 10-month-olds do. You know, the but
by the by the time they have.
Uh and so we we acquire in the first few
months of life all of those basic
concepts about the world. The world is
three-dimensional. There are objects
that can move independently. There are
you know, objects that, you know, move
that are not animated, so they follow
certain rules. There is, you know,
categories of objects. You don't need to
give names to them. We know the
difference between a table and a chair.
Um you know, and and then there you
know, objects have inertia, conservation
of momentum, things like that, right?
So, we learn this intuitively. Can we
train a system from video that will
acquire this type of common sense that,
you know, animals learn in days and and
humans months?
And the answer is yes. So, we have those
video systems, those Jepa architectures,
right? And, you know, and we determine
the level of abstraction at which we
train them.
Um so, they learn a representation of
the video from a window of 64 frames or
something like this, and
and they're trained you you take a piece
of video, you corrupt it
uh by masking a piece of it, and then
you run the full video to an encoder,
run the
corrupted video to another encoder,
uh and train a predictor to predict the
representation of the full video from
the partially corrupted one.
Uh and you train the whole thing end to
end simultaneously, and the system comes
up with a good abstract representation
of the world that only contains
information that is predictable.
Okay, and it only predicts
the information the part of the of the
world that is predictable. It's going to
ignore all the noise and details of, you
know, texture of your dress. Uh
although you should not ignore that
actually.
And and you know, and this kind of this
kind of detail. And so, um
So, that that's really the the way the
way to proceed. We've trained these
models. It's called V-Jepa 2, V for
video.
And it was trained on the equivalent of
100 years of video.
That seems like a lot, okay?
Cuz it doesn't learn as much as a almost
a human as a 2-year-old.
>> [laughter]
>> No.
Uh so, it doesn't learn for that long.
And
um
and it's not it's not a lot of video.
It's about It's about a day of YouTube
uploads. I mean, we we have like
enormous amounts of video. If you put a
number on it, it's about um
10 to the 15 to 10 to the 16 bytes at 2
megabytes per second.
This is
100 times more than the biggest LLMs,
okay? Cuz there's not that much text on
the internet. It's only about 10 to the
14 bytes.
Um and so, using video, you can train
with way more data than any LLMs, which
is why we're never going to get to human
level intelligence by training LLMs or
by training on text only, right? We need
the real world.
Okay, so you train this system on 100
years of video, and then we can test
whether the systems have acquired some
common sense. So, you show them a video
where something impossible happens. This
is, by the way, how we test babies
to figure out if they've learned a
particular concept like like like
gravity. You show babies scenario where
like a little car is on a on a platform,
and you push the car off the platform,
and the car appears to float in the air.
6-month-old babies don't pay attention.
10-month-olds go like this.
And I pay attention to it because, you
know, we're programmed to pay attention
to
the violations of our
prediction of our internal world model.
That's how That's how we know we have a
world model. Um and that's how you know,
psychologists test that. And so, we can
show a video where something impossible
occurs, like someone threw a ball in the
air a ball in the air, and the ball
stops, or it changes its shape to a
cube, or it disappears.
And the prediction error goes to the
roof
when you run the model on it
because it thinks it's like, I didn't
predict anything like this. That's
impossible. And so, that's the first
time I've I've seen
any kind of model that has some level of
common sense, and I think it's, you
know, But before we I think if you run
it for a a video prediction model,
it those scenarios, as as you say, if
you have the starting position and you
see it happen, you could also run it at
a full pixel level, and you would you
would probably very nicely also there be
able to measure that suddenly there's a
discrepancy with what your video model
predicts and what
um you know, like what you see in the
video.
I hope you'll pardon my French, but
absolutely no way in hell.
No, I I I don't agree. Like I think so I
think so if you if you have the starting
the starting, you know, point of the
video, and you run from that frame, you
run it forward, so you have a few
frames, and you run it forward the video
model, you will suddenly see that
there's a big deviation between what you
predict at the pixel. No, it's only
because you have the starting frame and
and this and that, but you could also
predict. Now, I agree with you that this
is like complete overkill for the task,
but I think you can also do it. You can
essentially do it up to the level that
you are you don't have enough
abstraction anymore.
>> It simply does not work.
We've tried to do this. I've tried to do
self-supervised learning from video for
15 years. The first 10 years I tried to
use generative models with latent
variables, okay? And the best method
that we have to do this today is
diffusion models. And with this, you
know, you can produce good videos.
There's no question. Uh it never worked
for natural videos. It worked for
stylized videos like video games,
um you know, basically already abstract
representations of video or like
segmentation maps, you know, to some
extent. But it never really worked, and
the reason it doesn't work is because
there is an infinite number of plausible
things that can happen in a video. And
when you train the system to make
predictions at the pixel level, the best
thing it can do, it can't represent a
distribution over all possible frames.
And so, the best thing it can do is,
uh you know, produce an average of all
the possible futures. So, if you use
diffusion models, you get around that
problem, but not entirely because the
your predictor can be completely wood
collapsed. So, it will produce a nice
video, but it's not going to understand
the underlying dynamics. So, um why do
we know this? We know this because we
have lots and lots of empirical evidence
of training generative models for
image representation. Okay, so there is
a very good example, which works great
for text, doesn't work for images. I
mean, it works, but not well. You take a
you take a piece of data, you corrupt it
by masking a piece of it, similar to
what I was describing earlier, and then
you train
some big model, basically an
autoencoder, to reconstruct the the full
input, whether it's text or images. In
the context of NLP, that's called BERT.
In the context of images, that's called
MAE, masked autoencoder.
Um and you do get some representation of
the text or the image. For images,
though, it's very expensive to train,
and the representation you get out of it
sucks. It really doesn't work very well.
The stuff that the method that produced
the best image representations are all
joint embedding architectures, which
means architectures that are trained
without a a criterion that attempts to
reconstruct pixels. You have to allow
the system to ignore information that
cannot be predicted. And if you put a
reconstruction criterion, it will have
to reconstruct everything, and you kill
it by doing it. And we know this. We
have lots of comparisons of MAE with
DINO, so you know about DINO.
Uh probably the best method for
self-supervised learning of image
representation. Probably the best method
for feature extraction,
you know,
Mhm.
Whatever, right? Whatever method you
use,
uh it this beats supervised learning
now, right? Self-supervised learning for
images with joint embedding architecture
beat
all approaches to supervised learning,
even those for which we have tons of
data. Uh this is new. Only happened in
the last year. Um so, DINO is one of
them. I-Jepa is another one. Uh I mean,
there's a bunch of you know, a small
number of methods like this that,
you know, beat
generative approaches for image
representation, and there's tons of
benchmarks for which we have images. So,
we I started realizing this about 5
years ago, and basically started, you
know, kind of
bashing generative models and completely
kind of try to brainwash everyone into
abandoning
generative AI, which is difficult
because, you know, everyone talks about
generative AI as
the thing.
Uh it didn't make me very popular among
some of my colleagues who work on LLMs.
So,
um you know, so so coming back to um
to to trying to solve robotics,
uh you mentioned a little bit uh
reinforcement learning. Um you know,
there are there's uh
you know, big fan of unsupervised
learning. There's also supervised
learning. Let's say in the mix of those
different things like um you know,
they probably have to work together in
some way, right? Like you you want to
figure out how the world work, probably
unsupervised.
Uh you want to learn how to kind of do
some tasks. That's probably has some
supervisory signal for sure.
Um and then, you know, reinforcement
learning is probably the thing that
actually gets it all to kind of you
know, fine-tune and the kind of all the
the actual moving parts of the robot and
and so on. So, how how would you kind of
see those things coming together? So,
about 10 years ago, uh
whenever I give a uh talk, I would show
a slide with a cake.
All right? I'm sure some of you have
seen it. Who has seen the cake?
Okay, great.
Uh that was about 10 years ago, and the
cake is an analogy.
I was trying to make the point.
Everybody at the time was like
completely into reinforcement learning.
I was telling people like reinforcement
learning is so inefficient in terms of
samples.
It's never going to amount to much. Um
except for games. Cuz for games, you can
generate so much data that it's fine.
Uh and that turned out to be true. Okay,
so the bulk of the cake, the genoise of
the cake, if you want,
is self-supervised learning. You learn
about the world, you learn to represent
it, you learn world models, you learn
prediction. Um that's self-supervised.
You don't need to
observe an expert, you don't need to
learn from anyone else. You just observe
the world go by. Okay?
Um that's the bulk of it. Most of your
parameters or whatever, your
intelligence, most of what you learn,
you learn this way.
Then there is a thin
>> And by the way, that would also be
embodiment agnostic. It would be yeah.
Yeah.
Um then there is a thin layer of either
supervised learning or imitation
learning or behavior cloning or inverse
reinforcement learning. There's several
names for it, but it's basically trying
to imitate or reproduce
uh
behavior of an expert, right? Or human.
Um that's a thin layer. Um
Most animals never go to that phase
because they never meet their parents.
>> [laughter]
>> So,
um [snorts] like octopus never meet
their parents. They get really smart in
just a few months. They live only 2
years. Um and then there is the cherry
on the cake, and that's reinforcement
learning. It's just like minor
fine-tuning because it's so inefficient.
Like if you if you were to train a
self-driving car from scratch to learn
to drive,
it's completely impractical. People
thought this was a possibility, you
know, back then 12 years ago.
Um and realized quickly that that was
completely impractical. Um it would
require too many trials. A car, you
know, driving next to a cliff would have
to run off the cliff a few dozen times
before realizing it's a bad idea. And
then a few other dozen times very
dangerous in Switzerland. Um
you know,
and then a few more dozen times to
realize how to not run off that cliff.
And then you're next to another cliff,
and you have to do it again, right?
Because it doesn't necessarily transfer
to the new situation. So,
you know,
reinforcement learning would work if I
learned at the right abstraction level,
you might have been able to generalize.
Yeah, but then this abstraction level is
given to you by self-supervised
learning, right? So, Yeah, but you can
build on top of it, let's say, like
Sure. Yeah. No, I mean, it's it's
necessary, right? I mean, clearly we
adjust our behavior uh you know, from
you know, action that we do in the world
and we realize we're not doing it right.
So, yeah, that that's a required cherry,
but it's only a minor But then, you
know, I have some colleagues that are
kind of big in reinforcement learning
and and um and the way they do it is
they use simulation to do it. And of
course, you know, there's still a little
bit of a gap,
but you know, they get kind of robots
with all kinds of things kind of they
figure out their their gait and this and
that and they you know, and then of
course, there's the gait of just walking
on a flat surface, that's pretty you
could design that.
But then, they also figure out how to
kind of crawl in very interesting ways,
you know, from over things and so on.
So, simulation is a thing that a little
bit decouples that cost. There's still a
cost to simulation, but it's not the
same cost as actually throwing the robot
off the you know, off the
you know, the [snorts] bricks or you
know, down the cliff or whatever, right?
I mean, for any particular set of task
or domain
or engineering problem, you're going to
have a very specific solution to it
that's going to you know, solve the
problem. Uh which is why, you know, we
have you know,
30 30 year old gadgets that can beat us
at chess,
uh but they're not necessarily
intelligent, right? Um so,
same thing same thing here, right? We
can we can cheat our way out or we can
engineer the hell out of it. Uh and you
know, solve problems of this type. So, I
mean, to train a set of reinforcement
learning to control a humanoid robot,
you basically have to simulate thousands
of copies of that humanoid robot in in
parallel on supercomputers and have them
do all kinds of stuff. And still in the
end,
>> Thousands you might do on one GPU, but
That's right. Possibly. Maybe well
well, not if you have perception. That
would be more expensive, but uh
but you know, in the end, it will only
be trained for this particular task,
this particular environment, and you
know, it'll be be brittle. A much more
efficient way to approach this is is
this idea of training world models. So,
you know,
ask a 10 year old
who's never done it before to accomplish
a new task. And you know, 10 year old
tend to accomplish new tasks pretty
often. But like, you know, ask a 10 year
old to clear the dinner table and fill
up the dishwasher. 10 year old can do it
the first time. Doesn't need to be
trained for it.
Um
you know, it might become more efficient
at doing it if you if it you know, does
it multiple times, but can do it the
first time. Why? Because of a world
model.
Um same thing for the
you know, 17 year old learning to drive.
The world model allows the 17 year old
to predict that
you know, if you're driving next to a
cliff and turn the turn the wheel to the
right, the car will run off the cliff
and nothing good will come out of this.
That's the that's a world model. That's
what allows us to solve a new task zero
shot without being trained
or to learn new tasks like driving
extremely quickly or skiing, right? Same
thing.
Uh first time you ski, you're kind of
hesitant and you kind of think about
everything you're supposed to do, and
then you become familiar and it becomes
kind of second nature, but that's the
second phase, right? That's the
difference that
uh psychologists call this system one
and system two. System one is tasks that
you can accomplish automatically without
thinking. System two is you use your
mental world model, that's all your
prefrontal cortex essentially. Um and
then you accomplish uh you can plan what
actions and you accomplish that task.
So, for you know, unsupervised learning,
I think you can you know, you can learn
from corpus of data, kind of understand
how the world works and so. But still
translating that to a particular
embodiment,
um there are challenges there, right?
Like because there you don't have an
unlimited amount of data anymore to kind
of just learn basic principles of how
the world functions and so on. So,
so how do you see that kind of
connection to the specific embodiment uh
to the you know, like people train
something on one embodiment and then
they have to transfer to another
embodiment, and you know, you have to
start all over. So, like not for
understanding the world, but for
understanding how you kind of do
something in the world. Okay, so here's
the experiment we did with V-JEPA 2.
And we have a new version coming out,
V-JEPA 2.1,
soon. So, V-JEPA 2, you you pretrain on
these 100 years of natural videos,
right? And the system learns to
represent video, it learns to fill in
the blanks in the video. That's the
first phase. Now you have a really good
representation of uh
of of you know, physical reality and a
good abstract representation and an
ability to predict, but not action
conditioned. So, it's not related to any
particular embodiment or you know,
there's no robot arm the system is
controlling. So, there's a second phase
where you fix the encoder
and you fine-tune the predictor and you
add an input, which is an action, right?
So, you have
position of the robot and state of the
world
and action that you observe um or that
you
send to the robot, and then you observe
the state of the world and the robot uh
right after. That requires
two sub models, a model of the robot
itself and a robot of the environment
and then maybe a model of the robot
itself, a model of the environment
cuz the environment might evolve by
itself, and maybe a model of the
interaction between the two, right? So,
if I if I move my hand here and I
close my hand, nothing happens. Okay?
That's completely under my control. But
if I move it next, you know, around the
the glass and I close my hand, now I
pick up the glass. So, that's an
interaction between the environment and
the the thing you the system
has to model all that. Now, it turns out
that fine-tuning phase where you have
state, action, next state, does not
require that much data.
And the data you can obtain through
simulation.
But it's not a simulation of a task, a
simulation of just the dynamics of a
system. So, you don't need a huge amount
of data. And the model that you get at
the end is generic, you can use it for
any task. So, now you can use that for
planning
motion of a robot to actually pick up a
glass or or pour water into a glass, and
then actually works.
So,
I switch to something something else,
like I want to
first go back in time
to you know, when computer vision
started working, at least you know, the
geometric parts are working long before
that, but let's say the semantic
understanding of the world. Uh I would
say that's essentially you know, CNNs
started making that work
about 15 years ago.
Um the
um
you know, so there we had a very useful
clear inductive bias
of hey, you know, like if I see
something here or there, it doesn't
matter. I want the same filters, the
same thing, the same understanding.
So,
are there things like this?
Um you You then then there's also of
course, uh what is it? The the the the
bitter lesson that's saying like forget
all of that, you know, like if I see a
cat up there, it's probably like a
floating cat. So, it's something very
different than when I see it. I should
not see a cat up there. So, I suppress
that and so I don't want the same
filters up there than I want them down
there and and stuff like that. And so,
eventually if you have enough data,
you know, like forget about all these
inductive biases and so on.
On the other hand, I'm very frustrated
in robotics, you know, like this is now
with relay and stuff like that also, but
you know, indeed a big part of the field
is like, "Okay, I've trained this relay
with like a camera up here and like my
arm is exactly up there and this exact
configuration. And actually, by the way,
I have a fixed background. Nobody can,
you know, this wouldn't work here. I
need the exact background, the exact
pixel, by the way, indeed in their cases
often, which is completely, but
um
but essentially, um
you know, a lot of that is essentially
perfectly predictable with, you know, we
have methods to kind of, you know,
[snorts] transfer that to predict it and
so on. Um
Where do you see the, you know, like the
you know, are there inductive biases
similar to what we had with, um you
know, with with the convolutional kind
of um shift invariance essentially that
we're bringing in? Like are there
similar things that you see on the
horizon or like things that could be
applicable for the things we're trying
out now in embodied AI?
So, you you can always, as you say, you
can always uh replace
inductive biases in your architecture or
prior knowledge in your architecture
like, you know, convolutional nature
>> [snorts]
>> um
by more data.
And if your training is mostly
self-supervised, perhaps
you know, you have essentially from
video, you have an infinite supply of
data. You have more data than you can
you can you can you can manage.
Uh so, maybe there are the
the type of
uh prior knowledge that we, you know,
put into encoders like like the
convolutional nature
are no longer necessary. And we see
this, you know, in the
Okay, here's an interesting uh
uh piece of data.
The
in the academic world, in the
publications,
uh the the best computer vision systems,
most of the papers use transformers,
vision transformer VITs, or some
variation variation of it.
Uh
video not quite the case because
transformers on video start to become
really expensive if you want to do high
resolution.
Um but
you can get the same performance with
convolutional nets.
And you will get it with less data. But
if you have data, why would you kind of
you know, take the risk of getting a
lower performance. And also, there is uh
work by very interesting work by my NYU
colleague, former fair colleague
actually, Saining Xie, uh
uh something called ConvNeXt. So, he is
sort of carefully fine-tuned the all the
tricks, you know, in the convolutional
net
uh transposing some of the tricks that
are used in transformer and say, "Look,
you know, you actually get, you know,
the same performance with ConvNeXts as
you do with transformers if you do all
the right tricks if you send the spend
the same amount of effort on them." So,
it's not there's nothing really
intrinsic uh about the architecture
there,
uh at least for images and certainly for
video.
Um the thing is it starts getting
impractical
when you deal with video. If you have,
you know, high resolution video, um high
frame rate, then the number of tokens
that you need to feed to your
transformer for that becomes sort of
impractically large. And so, then the
computation is ridiculous. And here is a
piece of data that's important. Every
single real-time vision system uses
convolutional nets. They don't use
transformers. Your car, your
self-driving car has in Europe, every
car sold in Europe has to have a
uh automatic emergency braking system.
And it's a camera looking at the
windshield uh that stops the car when
there is an obstacle. Most of them have
something that allows you to drive more
or less automatically on the highway.
Every single one of them uses
convolutional net. Every single one of
them. Because you need real time and
you're not going to get that from
transformers.
At least not today.
So, um
you know, if we look at, you know, we're
also embodied, obviously. Um we have
our, you know, our brain up there that's
helping us figure out how to act in the
world.
We're using, you know, whatever 20 watts
of power for doing that. Um
I think part of it is really to have a
very adaptive, you know, level at which
we actually read out the, you know, like
abstraction level um
um and so on. But like what do you see
on the horizon? What are the kind of
things that can bring us to or what is
still missing actually? What what are
the things that we should as a maybe
research community really focus on uh to
to to, you know, to get to something
like that? It's a hardware issue. It's a
it's actually a device issue. It's not
just uh you know, computer architecture
issue.
>> the algorithms are solved?
I mean, I think the algorithms are are
not the issue the main issue for like
power consumption. Here is the problem.
Um
the in the brain,
The weights are in place. Uh The weights
are in place. The weights are in place,
right? Exactly. So,
uh in the brain, you
you know, the number of parameters in a
neural net is like a synapse in the
brain. It's not quite the same analogy,
but let's let's make this assumption,
right?
Um
So, we have one physical synapse and one
physical [snorts] neuron per
virtual neuron, if you want. Okay. Um
Whereas in a computer implementation of
a neural net or deep learning system,
we reuse the same
piece of hardware, the same silicon, to
compute the output of multiple neurons
and multiple synapses.
Okay? So, what that means and the reason
we need to do this is because our
fabrication technology is too big and
too fast.
So, we have to use what's called
hardware multiplexing. You have to reuse
the same piece of hardware to compute
multiple parts of of the neural net.
And what that means is that you have to
get data from memory and shuffle it
through the
computational engine,
right? And put the result back to
memory.
All the energy, all the power is spent
getting data from the memory and writing
it back.
So, the difference between a classical
CPU and the GPUs that are optimized for
for for neural nets is that the GPUs
have this kind of hierarchical memory
that allows to kind of minimize the
amount of traffic to memories that is
far away and slower so that you you save
quite a bit of energy, but you cannot
with current technology, you simply
cannot
have
one computing device per neuron or
synapse in your neural net.
You would have to go to like some sort
of exotic analog technology for this
which does not exist, you know, it might
pop up in the future. It could be
spintronics, it could be carbon
nanotubes, it could be, you know,
whatever some optical widget, but it
doesn't exist at the moment. If you're
going to use CMOS, the technology is too
big and too fast and you have to reuse
the same piece of hardware for different
parts of your neural net. You have to
shuffle data. That's where all your
energy is going to go. So, in other
words, if we could have an analog
asynchronous
three-dimensional stacking of elements,
we might actually get there. Yeah, and
uh you know, possibly.
And it would have to be
it wouldn't have to be as fast as our
current electronics because it would be
massively parallel and way more than
current systems. But you would need to
>> do we run at? Uh we run at like 10
hertz. Okay. In the sense of your retina
works at about 15 hertz, which is why,
you know, cinema is at 24 frames per
second because you can't see
you know,
uh you you perceive the frames as
motion, right? Uh
And and the the whole process of going
from your retina to your if
inferotemporal cortex or your motor
cortex for reacting to a visual stimulus
is is 100 milliseconds for perception,
another 100 milliseconds to figure out
what to do. So, your your feedback loop
when you
see an obstacle in the street and you
need to brake, you know, hit the brake
pedal for your for your car, that's like
300 milliseconds, a third of a second.
Incredibly slow.
Uh cats are faster.
Okay, which is why because they have
small brains, which is why, you know,
they can stand in front of a cobra and
when the cobra starts to attack, they go
boom, right? We can't do this as humans.
We're just too slow. Um so, uh
you know, we we're going to require some
some non-volatile memory storage
technology that is incredibly compact,
right? We're talking like, you know,
nanometers for
you know, a single analog memory type
thing.
Which, you know, biology figured out how
to do, but we don't know what to do what
to do with current fabrication.
>> other part, so that would be like, you
know,
potentially like a frozen brain or
something, right? A key thing about us
is we can adapt. We can keep adjusting.
We don't have to first learn and then,
you know, infer. Well, this this thing
would be would have to be,
you know, to learn in the loop. In fact,
there is this concept that people were,
you know, kind of thinking of in the
1980s and and 90s where people were
working on analog neural net
implementations.
And it was
the fact that when you start to get to
these small devices, the characteristic
of each device is different.
Um you have a lot of variability from
one device to a to another on a single
chip. And so, you can't just program the
system with, you know, known weights
that have been trained offline
uh because the characteristic of the
components uh vary so much. And so, you
have to train the system in the loop
with the characteristic of the of of the
chip itself, which means that that
system is not reproducible. It's unique.
It's it's mortal, if you want. Okay?
Like like human brain, you can't copy a
make another copy of human brain.
So, so
okay. So, so, you know, like so
essentially, what do you see on the
like, you know, is there anything out
there on the horizon where, you know,
not not back to the hardware in in in
the 80s or so, but more in in
algorithmically of of bringing learning
in the loop. Uh for you know, for
embedded systems or for systems that act
in the world and have to keep adjusting
and also
partially also based on their own um you
know, like if we get hurt and then you
know, like we can actually adapt and we
change our gait a bit and this and that
and so on. Um
what's what's what's there? Like can we
expect to see kind of learning systems
in the loop essentially coming
>> I think the answer is clearly yes and I
actually don't think it's particularly
challenging conceptual
uh problem. I mean, I don't think we
need to invent anything new to be able
to do you know, online adaptation. We do
this all the time, right? If
uh
you know, you
you know, you you you try to pick up a
pick up an object and you realize the
object is like way heavier than you
realize. This is actually way heavier
than I thought.
>> [laughter]
>> It's like pretty thick glass actually.
Um
and you know, you immediately adapt.
Your world model that predicted like you
know, how how much force you had to
apply to lift this object
you know, adapts in milliseconds. This
is done actually most probably possibly
not entirely clear but probably in the
cerebellum. Cerebellum is a
very special
piece of the brain that actually has
most of our neurons in a in a human
brain actually in the cerebellum not in
the cortex.
Uh
it's like 50 million neurons in the
cerebellum only 16 million in the cortex
which is weird.
Uh but they you know, mostly the the
theories about the cerebellum is fast
adaptation to kind of changing
situations. So
again also when we observe something
that violates our internal model of the
world, we're programmed to pay attention
to it because you know, we need to learn
from it.
Cuz that means our world model was
inaccurate. Also, it could be a tiger
jumping at us, right? That we didn't
foresee. It can kill us, right? So we
have to pay attention to
uh distortion from prediction. So that's
the cherry, right? That's not the
cherry. That's the adjustment of your
world model. It's not supervised. It's
completely self-supervised. This is not
related to a task.
>> That's reinforcement learning, right?
It's not reinforcement learning.
Absolutely not. It's self-supervised
learning. It's Okay, I observe something
going on in the world and my prediction
was wrong and now I wait a little. I
observe what actually occurred. I adjust
my prediction my predictor. You know,
it's a Jeff architecture. There's no
task to accomplish. There's no
reinforcement. There's no value
function. Nothing like that. Just
prediction error.
Okay? And you adapt your your model and
that's generic. It doesn't it's not task
dependent. Welcome to the AI House
Davos.
Our next panel on the summit stage will
begin in 15 minutes. Okay, we still have
I guess I guess we have some time.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay, so anyways, I think we have to
wrap it up. So so maybe to finish um
where do you see things like 10 years
from now? Like in in embodied AI in
particular, right? In terms of robots,
in terms of what what can they do and
what's still out what's still unsolved?
So I'm I'm just you know, starting a a
new very ambitious company
uh with the idea that we're going to be
able to solve that problem within a few
years and basically have systems that
understand the physical world or any
modality you throw at them
um can build world models, can use those
world models to plan,
uh can build hierarchical world models,
so you can do hierarchical planning Mhm.
and then basically be the blueprint for
the future
AI systems um that are much more
powerful than you know, LLMs that we
have currently. It's completely
different paradigm, non-generative as I
said because it's those Jeff
architectures. Um
not
not using autoregressive token
prediction but using planning. Okay, so
systems that can predict the
consequences of their actions which I
think is the only
decent way to build agentic systems
uh except for real world applications.
And so I'm seeing a future where this is
going to be the next AI revolution.
Okay? We're going to have another AI
revolution
brought about by this and I'm building a
company around this idea with and I
think it's the right time to do it
because we already have results that
show that this approach works. You know,
we can train from video. We get systems
that have some level of common sense. We
can train predictive models on top of
them. World models, we can use them for
planning. And so that points to the
direction that you know, we we see a
clear path to much more powerful AI
systems than we currently have.
When you say they're not generative,
they're generative but across the
different level at at different levels
of abstraction in a sense. Well,
generative my definition of generative
is that you reproduce the input signals
or you predict the input signals. Here
you make predictions at representational
level. Mhm. Okay? That's not generative
in my in my world but Yeah, yeah, but I
mean okay. Good. Thank you very much.
Thank you. Thank you.